Finding Aid for Henry J. Meyer and Suzanne M. Meyer Papers, 1867-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry J. Meyer and Suzanne M. Meyer Papers 1867-2000, 1926-2000
Meyer family.
1.3 linear foot
85301 Aa 2
Henry J. Meyer was a social worker and University of Michigan professor of sociology. Suzanne M. Meyer was secretary of the Ann Arbor Human Relations Commission, also assistant to the director of student activities and organizations at the University of Michigan. She was also involved both in the Tutorial and Cultural Relations Project and the Opportunity Awards Program. The collection includes professional papers and files relating to their travels and activities abroad.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were transferred in four donations from Henry and Suzanne Meyer (donor no. 6625 ) in 1981, 1995 and 2001. Additional materials were donated by Tamar Chute (donor no. 9127 ) in 2001.
The collection is open to research.
Henry Meyer, sociologist and educator, was born in 1913 in Birmingham, Alabama. From the age of 2, he lived in Meridian, Mississippi. Upon graduation from Meridian High School in 1930, he entered the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, and proceeded to earn his B. A. (1934), M. A. (1937), and Ph. D. (1939) in sociology.
Upon completing his doctorate, Meyer taught at Washington State College in Pullman, Washington. In 1946, he was appointed associate professor, then professor, of sociology at New York University. In 1957 he became professor of social work and of sociology at the University of Michigan. He remained here for twenty years, retiring in 1978 as emeritus professor of sociology.
From 1957 to 1970, Meyer was the head of the first interdisciplinary doctoral program in social work and social science in the country. In 1970, he initiated under joint sponsorship of the Schools of Social Work and Public Health at the University of Michigan the Social Work Education and Population Planning Training Program for social welfare personnel in less-developed countries. From 1972 through 1978, this project, funded by the United States Agency for International Development (USAID) saw him travel to Iran, India and Southeast Asia. The co-editor or co-author of several books and journal articles, he was in 1974 the first social work professor to receive the University of Michigan's Distinguished Service Award.
Throughout his career, and outside of the classroom, Meyer held a number of different and important positions. During 1935-1936, he worked for the Washtenaw County office of the Federal Emergency Relief Agency (FERA) where he was dismissed for rallying welfare recipients to demand more adequate relief allotments. His dismissal spawned a controversy in the community as reflected in local newspapers and attracted national attention. During World War II, he held various positions in the National War Labor Board and its successor, the National Wage Stabilization Board. After participating in mediation of a threatened nation-wide strike in the telephone industry in 1944, he was named vice chairman of the National Telephone Commission set up by the War Labor Board. Upon termination of the War Labor Board in December 1945, he was appointed chairman of the Fourth Regional Wage Stabilization Board (Atlanta office), leaving that position to return to teaching.
In 1949 he began what was to be a summer-long position as technical consultant for the Military Government of Germany that was undertaking a study of a severely-bombed small city, Darmstadt. As that training and research survey developed, it was extended for three years during which time Meyer continued to serve as a technical advisor.
Henry Meyer died on October 29, 2000, in Ann Arbor.
Suzanne Mahler Meyer was born in 1914, educated in the Detroit public schools and the University of Michigan (B. A. 1935). Since coming to Ann Arbor in 1957 she has been involved in civic matters. Participating vigorously in local civil rights activities, particularly with respect to discrimination in housing, she was the first employee of the Ann Arbor Human Relations Commission. Subsequently she held the post of Assistant to the Vice-President for Student Activities and Organization at the University of Michigan. She also took part in the University of Michigan's Tutorial Project and the Opportunity Awards Program.
Henry J. Meyer and Suzanne M. Meyer Papers include some material on his student days at the University of Michigan, files on his work for and controversial dismissal from the Washtenaw County Welfare Agency and his research and foreign travels. Suzanne Meyer's papers relate largely to he work with the Ann Arbor Human Relations Commission and her travels in Europe n 1950 and 1972. The Meyer Family collection is divided into three series: Henry Meyer, Travels and Foreign Activities, and Suzanne Meyer.
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Human Relations Commission.; Civil rights--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Darmstadt (Germany); Germany (West)--Description and travel.; Myers family.; Tutors and tutoring.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Tutorial and Cultural Relations Project.; University of Michigan. Opportunity Award Program.; Washtenaw County Welfare Agency.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects: Visual Materials
Darmstadt (Germany); Germany (West)--Description and travel.; Meyer, Henry Joseph, 1913-; Meyer, Suzanne M.
Contributors:
Meyer, Henry Joseph, 1913-; Meyer, Suzanne M.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Henry Meyer
  The Henry Meyer series contains personal and biographical items such as his vita, faculty personnel record, grade slips, an autograph book, newspaper clippings announcing his graduation, family correspondence regarding his student life at the University of Michigan and his career choice, an article on camping he authored for the New York Times, announcements of a book publication, selected correspondence and articles detailing his life's accomplishments at his retirement, obituaries, a sampling of condolence correspondence and a memorial book. Of particular interest is the file detailing his dismissal from the Washtenaw County Welfare Agency. Included are letters from his family, correspondence from Milton Kemmitz, a co-worker also disciplined by the agency, and official documentation of the incident. Information on his dealings while involved with the National War Labor Board, although predominantly newspaper clippings, are also included in this series and provide information largely on Henry Meyer's arbitration work in the AT&T telephone strike. This series also includes correspondence, articles, course material, and, notably, Washtenaw County land deeds from the late 1800s, relating to Meyer's research into Ann Arbor's early Jewish community.
  - Anderson, Nels, Correspondence and Article 1973-1981 (Box 1)
  - Articles and Reports 1940-1968 (Box 1)
  - Biographical/ Personal 1926-2000, 4 folders (Box 1)
    (includes graduation photograph, correspondence with family while a student at University of Michigan 1932-1936, retirement correspondence, 1977, obituaries, condolence correspondence, and a memorial book)
  - Correspondence 1981-1997, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Gary, Lawrence, Correspondence and Vita 1996-1998 (Box 1)
  - Henry Meyer Fellowship Fund/ Award 1985-1999, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - McNeely, Roger, Correspondence and Articles 1996-1998 (Box 1)
  - Munday, Brian, Correspondence and Vita 1989-1997 (Box 1)
  - National War Labor Board 1942-1947, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Regional Wage Stabilization Board 1946 (Box 1)
  - Proseminar in Social Work (SW 800) 1997-2000 (Box 1)
  - Research Material, Ann Arbor's Early Jewish Community--Land Deeds 1867-1892 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw County Welfare Agency
    - Correspondence 1935 (Box 1)
    - Documentation relating to dismissal (letters, memoranda, reports) 1935-1936 (Box 1)
    - Official Reports 1935 (Box 1)
- Travels and Foreign Activities
  The Travels and Foreign Activities series consists predominantly of letters written home by Henry Meyer while working on his community survey project in Darmstadt, Germany. Suzanne joined him for one of his three years in Germany and her letters home are also included. Jointly, they provide a great deal of description of Germany after World War II as well as civilian life. A photograph album depicts the state of Germany while Henry worked there. Photos include mostly landmarks and people--all of which are unidentified. Suzanne's diary while in Germany (1950) also documents their short stop in Paris. Her entries consist mainly of day to day occurrences, but also include her thoughts on how she finds the country after the close of World War II. The series also contains files on the Meyers' trip to England in 1972 and their 1972 Meyers travels through the Far East when Henry worked on a population planning project there.
  - Darmstadt, Germany 1949-1952
    - Letters
      - From Henry to family May 1949-July 1949 (Box 1)
      - From Henry to family August 1949-1950 (Box 1)
      - From Henry and Suzanne to family 1950-1951 (Box 1)
    - Diary of Suzanne while in Germany 1950 (Box 1)
    - Photograph Album detailing stay in Darmstadt, circa 1949-1952 (Box 1)
  - England 1972 (Box 2)
    - Letters from Henry and Suzanne to family 1972 (Box 2)
  - Far East 1972
    - Letters from Henry and Suzanne to family 1972 (Box 2)
- Suzanne Meyer
  The final series, that of Suzanne Meyer, contains an interesting mix of materials. Documented are civil rights cases brought before the Ann Arbor Human Relations Commission through the years 1957-1972, official reports from the commission from 1961 to 1966, in addition to campus housing discrimination information (largely different official summations and statements of policies) from 1959 to 1965. In her capacity as assistant to the director for Student Activities and Organizations, she also collected various papers from the University of Michigan's tutorial project. Included are many hand-outs which were given to new tutors, as well as policy statements and reports. A final sub-series contains a report and some newspaper clippings, along with a few odd items regarding the University of Michigan's Opportunity Awards Program, which benefited the "technically disadvantaged," or minority students.
  - Ann Arbor Human Relations Commission
    - Case Documentations 1957-1972 (Box 2)
    - Campus Housing Discrimination Cases 1959-1965 (Box 2)
    - Reports 1961-1966 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Tutorial Project 1963-1965 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Opportunity Awards Program 1963-1970 (Box 2)